

Saumitra Mazumder



SAMazumder



SAMazumder

About Me ————

Experience in model development and model validation/audit. Solid knowledge of a range of quantitative finance, risk management (e.g., VaR/Expected Shortfall for Market Risk, credit portfolio models, stress testing), derivatives models and pricing theory. Interested in the intersection of machine learning, quantitative finance, and climate change. Thorough and analytical: able to apply logic to solve problems. Excellent verbal and written communication skills. Proven ability to collaborate effectively with diverse individuals and strengthen relationships to achieve well-designed solutions.

Education ——

M.Sc. Applied Mathematics Toronto Metropolitan University (formerly Ryerson University) 2020-2022 Ryerson Graduate Fellowship, Graduate Development Award, Mathematics Graduate Award

B.Sc. Mathematics and Economics Toronto Metropolitan University (formerly Ryerson University) 2015-2019 Dean's List 2016, 2017 Ryerson Barbell Club, Ryerson Math Problem Solving Club

Knowledge

Financial Mathematics Financial Time Series Analysis, Risk Measures, ASRF model, Derivative Pricing, Regression, Monte Carlo/Copulae/Variance-Covariance

Methods, Decision Theory.

Tools R (Dplyr, QRM, xts, dynlm), Python (NumPy, SciPy, PANDAS, XG-

Boost. SKLearn), MATLAB, SAS, LATEX, SQL.

Recent Employment History

2022-Current Ernst & Young LLP

FRSM

Staff consultant in the Financial Services Risk Management Group - Consulting Practice.

Assisting clients in auditing their credit risk models (ECL, PD, LGD, EAD) on both the retail and non-retail side per IFRS 9 standards. Major tasks included validating the conceptual soundness of clients credit risk models as well as code replication and corroboration. Assisted in development/re-development of IFRS9, CECL and stress tasting models post M&A by client firm

testing models post M&A by client firm.

2022-2022 Scotiabank

Scotiabank Velocity Intern - Model Audit, Credit Risk. Toronto, Canada Member of the team auditing ECL models (PD, CCI, EAD, LGD) per IFRS 9 guidance provided by OSFI. Used internal audit methodology to provide independent oversight of models.

Closed audit issues pertaining an end-to-end retail model procedure.

2018-2022

Toronto Metropolitan University, Department of Mathematics Graduate Research Assistant under Dr. Foivos Xanthos

Completed research in Functional Analysis and its use in coherent and convex risk measures on L^p -spaces.

Developed empirical algorithms to implement general-moment market risk measures using R and Python.

Analysed financial data using non-parametric methods to demonstrate the potential benefits of general-moment models.

Graduate Teaching Assistant

Lead tutorials for graduate and undergraduate courses. Marking and test invigilation for assigned courses.

Teaching Assistant for various mathematics courses. In particular, assisted students in becoming familiar with fundamental and advanced statistical concepts like MLE estimation, hypothesis testing, linear and non-linear regression models and solving various statistical problems using R.

Undergraduate Research Assistant under Dr. Foivos Xanthos

Completed research on time series, probability theory, functional analysis and their applications to financial instruments. In particular, modelled credit risk via the asymptotic single factor Vasicek (Merton) credit risk model.

Major Projects

Graduate Thesis STATISTICAL CONSISTENCY FOR RISK MEASURES WITH THE LEBESGUE PROPERTY

When estimating the risk of a P&L from historical data or Monte Carlo simulation, the robustness of the estimate is important. Analyzed a refined notion of robustness that applies to tail-dependent law-invariant convex risk measures on Orlicz spaces.